Rev. Eugene Alphonse Solega Collection CPAA 94.15
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Rev. Eugene Alphonse Solega Collection
1934-1983
CPAA 94.15
Connecticut Polish American Archives
5.0 Linear feet
The collection of Rev. Eugene A. Solega, native of Hartford, CT, shows the life of a second generation Polish American priest. Rev. Solega held several pastoral assignments in Connecticut. Throughout his life he was involved with several organizations, religious or not, including several social organizations helping women, young people, and displaced persons from Europe. The collection holds items related to his education and pastoral work, including handwritten notes, photographs, and newspaper articles.
Eugene Alphonse, Solega, Rev.
Scope and Contents note
This collection spans most of the life of Rev. Eugene Solega, covering mostly his educational and religious life. It does include his parent’s naturalization papers from before his birth but the bulk of material is within the dates of 1934 to 1983. Besides some medical records from later in his life, there is nothing included that relates to his death. Most items are personal notebooks from seminary, correspondence, official programs/memorabilia from services or ceremonies, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
Biographical/Historical note
Rev. Eugene A. Solega was born in Hartford on June 10, 1915 to parents Adam and Tekla Solega, Polish immigrants. He attended S.S. Cyril and Methodius parochial school in Hartford. He then attended St. Thomas Seminary in Bloomfield for six years. Bishop McAuliffe appointed him to study philosophy and theology at St. Mary’s Seminary in Baltimore, MD. and was ordained on May 22, 1941. His first assignment was to St. Joseph parish in Rockville where he served from June 29, 1941 to November 11, 1949. His second appointment was to St. Mary’s church in Middletown from Nov. 11, 1949 until April 27, 1960, where he was also the principal of the religious school. During his time in Middletown, he became the moderator of the Middletown District of Catholic Women and the Associate Director of Catholic Charities. His third appointment was to St. Bridget church in Moodus on April 27, 1960. His final appointment was for the St. John’s church in Old Saybrook on June 5, 1969. Father Solega participated in various community activities throughout his life. He was a member of the Community Chest Board of Directors, Red Cross Advisory Board, Association of Polish Priests in Connecticut and chaplain of the Knights of Columbus and Catholic War Veterans. He was a president of the Middletown Exchange Club and worked with the Catholic Youth Organization in the state together with Msgr. John Wodarski. He became a Director of Diocesan of Resettlement for displaced persons to the US from Europe in the 1950’s. He died on August 18, 1985.
Association of Polish Priests in Connecticut; Catholic Church. Diocese of Norwich (Conn.) – History; Clergy -- Connecticut; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Minutes.; Photographs; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- Middletown -- Church history; St. John's Church (Old Saybrook, Conn.)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – Naturalization papers of Tekla and Adam Solega (parents); life insurance policies., 1937; 1941; 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – Newspaper clippings about ordination to priesthood, May 22, 1941. One full edition of The Catholic Transcript from the same date with Solega’s photo. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – health insurance, doctors visits, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – Association of Polish Priests in Connecticut, visit of Polish bishops, related correspondence, minutes, 1975-1976. Polish Studies Program Report, 1976 from CCSU, “Poles in the Bicentennial U.S.A” by Msgr. Fiedorczyk, 1977., 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega - Association of Polish Priests in Connecticut, the National Czestochowa Shrine Trust Appeal, related correspondence and publicity, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega - Association of Polish Priests in Connecticut, 1983. Minutes of the previous meeting and letter about "Radio Free Europe." (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – Address at the Unknown Soldier Memorial Day, Grove Hill Cemetery, Rockville, CT (in English), May 30, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – various speeches, addresses, testimonials, programs & a packet of jokes about different topics (1947, 1959, 1962 were dates notated), 1947-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – Homily for 75th Anniversary of SS. Cyril & Methodius (in Polish), April 24, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – testimonial dinner honoring Rev. Solega retiring Associate Director of Catholic Charities, March 3, 1964; Rev. Eugene A. Solega – testimonial Guest Book, March 3, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – 25th anniversary of Priesthood, 1966: celebration and newspaper article (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – 40th Anniversary of Priesthood, related correspondence, invitations, clippings, May 24, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – St. Bridget Centennial Anniversary Booklet, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – St. Bridget Centennial, clippings and photographs, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – St. Bridget church, Moodus, CT, death register from May 12, 1960 – March 15, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – writings related to mystics (1936), hope and hypnotism. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – book reviews related to economics, socialism, and ethics. No date noted but probably from time in seminary., 1935-1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – papers and readings from seminary, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – invitations for religious celebrations and testimonials from all over Connecticut, 1947-1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – notes on various religious topics. (Mostly Bible related), 1936-1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – correspondence with organizations, postcards, notice of assignments to churches, personal cards, 1936-1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – Knights of Columbus Old Saybrook, CT services/meetings. 1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – holy cards 1934,1958-1982, Bulk, 1958-1982; 1934-1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – The Stella Matutina Quarterly, St. Thomas Seminary, 1934, 1935, 1941 (Solega’s Graduation), The Golden Jubilee Celebration, 1947, 1934-1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – post cards with local churches and tourist attractions. Only a few dates given on correspondence., Bulk, 1941-1950; 1941-1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – individual income tax., 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – newspaper clippings related to Rev. Solega, 1935-76, 1935-1976 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega - clippings related to Polish American clergy, political issues, & sports, 1941-1950 (Musiel in one) (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – Toastmaster at Felician Sisters Centennial, Nov. 3, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – resolution of participation in the Conn. District Exchange Clubs. No dates notated, just researched dates of conventions., 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – St. Bridget Parrish annual financial report and regulations, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Various publications and pamphlets, The Catholic Advocate, 1944-1950. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – misc. catholic memorabilia and notes, 1950's and 1960's., 1950-1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- “The Herald St. Joseph School News”, v. I, no.1, Spring Edition; “The Heynal. St. Joseph School”, Rockville, CT, v. II, no. 2. Dates are the years he was in Rockville., 1941-1949 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Graduation pictures from St. Joseph School, Rockville, CT 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Anthony Sadlak, congressman at large, testimonial dinner, Rockville, CT 1947 (2 photos) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega participation in Second National Conference on Catholic Youth Work, April 28, 1949 (1 photo) (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Collection of photographs – blessing of construction for a new church by Bishop O’Brien, participating priests: Solega, H. Fiedorczyk, Kloczko, Bombolinski, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – 2nd Annual Meeting, Norwich Diocesan Bureau of Social Services, May 6, 1956 (1 photo); National Catholic Cem. Conference, Washington D.C., Oct. 22, 1959 (1 photo), 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Collection of photographs – St. Mary’s church, Middletown CT, inside church 40th Anniversary, 1952. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Collection of photographs – golden Jubilee of St. Mary’s church, Middletown, CT. No date known for event, dates represent Solega's appointment there., 1949-1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega receives award for service to Catholic Charities, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega participates in Veterans organization events (5 photos), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega participating in meeting of Priests in Baltimore Seminary, on 20th Anniversary of Priesthood, Nov. 1961 and 25th Anniversary of Priesthood, Nov. 1966, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega participates in Msgr. Nowakowski 40th Anniversary to Priesthood, 1960. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega participating in First Communion pictures from early 1940’s, 1943, 1945-47, 1954, 1960-67, 1940-1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega and Rev. Malanowski – various photographs, one from 1952, no other dates noted. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, graduation ceremony at St. Mary’s, Middletown, various photographs, 1952-1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, the Exchange Club Events –various photographs, 1949-73, 1949-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega with Gen W. Anders during his visit to the US, Oct. 1950 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Cardinal Stefan Wyszynski with Bishop of Norwich V. Hines in Rome, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – celebration of the First Mass; photos with Msgr. Musiel., 1949-1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, photographs from St. Mary’s: altar boys, basketball team, funeral of a priest, 1949-1960 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega with Bishop O’Brian and Msgr. Grady, 1962?, celebration for 50th anniversary of priesthood for Msgr. Grady. (Possible) (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, St. Bridget, Moodus, photographs from various events (1964) (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, 40th Anniversary to Priesthood, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, collection of portraits of various priests. Only date represented is 1975, although many of them are clearly older. (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, photographs from various events religious and non religious, 1937-1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega at a book fair with Rev. Kloczko and Rev. Cronin, 1960. (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega presentation of a check to the Pro-life Council, [1970’s?], 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, letter from American Relief for Poland Rockville chapter, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Brief history of St. Joseph’s Parish, Rockville, CT (typed 2 pg.), 1952. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, the Exchange Club with related correspondence and publications, Freedom Shrine information, Old Saybrook, CT. 1964-1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, a President of the Exchange Club - correspondence, resignation letters, Constitution and By-Laws, 1974, 1979-1980., 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – National Federation of Priests Council, Priest Senate, 1977-1981, correspondence of Father Stanley Szczapa. (Transferred to St. Johns in 1977) (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega St. John parish, office of Religious Education, minutes, correspondence 1977-79, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, Emmaus – retreat for priests in Norwich Diocese, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, St. Bridget church bulletin, Moodus, CT 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, St. Bridget church bulletin, Moodus, CT 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- “Poland at War” by Count Jerzy Potocki, Polish Ambassador to the United States, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, will executor for Victoria K. McCarthy (housekeeper for St. John’s), obituary, last will, income tax returns, related correspondence,1983. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Rev. Eugene Solega’s notes from seminary on homilitics, patrology and history of the Church, history of philosophy, public speaking, cosmology, economics, education, dogma, canon law, scripture, and morals 1935-1941 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Collection of books, pamphlets, anniversary and holiday booklets related to Polish American organizations 1940’s-1980’s, 1940-1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega recognition dinner for his service in the Exchange Club at Middletown, CT Jan. 6, 1968 (photo album) (Box 4)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega – BA certificate from the Seminary in Baltimore, June, 1937 (Box 4)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega, 25th Anniversary dinner class of 1930, Hartford, May 24, 1955 (photograph) (Box 4)
- Best wishes to Rev. Eugene A. Solega from members of St. John’s Parrish, Old Saybrook, CT (includes signatures), 1971 (Box 4)
- Rev. Eugene A. Solega 30th Anniversary of Priesthood best wishes from parishioners, St. John’s, Old Saybrook, 1971 (Box 4)
- Knights of Columbus ribbon., 1977-1985 (Box 4)
- Small box with name tag, small cross, and various small objects., 1941-1985 (Box 4)